Ehrmann, Henry W. (Heinrich); Papers ger013
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Henry W. Ehrmann Papers
1932-1998
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Ehrmann, Henry Walter, 1908-1994.
ger013
4 cubic ft.
The Henry Ehrmann Papers are focused on Ehrmann's scholarly career as a political scientist and a professor of law and his participation in the program of re-education of German prisoners-of-war in the 1940s. The material also documents Ehrmann's association with other universities and institutions in the United States and Europe. The correspondence from and to the former German prisoners-of-war who met Ehrmann during the reeducation program organized by the War Department include letters - in several cases written by the prisoners' family members as well - almost entirely dating from the period immediately subsequent to the POWs' release and their return to Germany. Therefore, they are a valuable source of information about the living conditions in occupied Germany, the country's political transformation, and the correspondents' adaptation to new circumstances. Letters in the general correspondence subseries are, for the most part, related to Ehrmann's contacts with his fellow scholars and with academic or political institutions. Also included are speeches, lectures, lecture notes, and newspaper articles, 1941–1984. Ehrmann was a professor of political science at the University of Colorado, the University of California at San Diego, and Dartmouth University, and worked on French politics, labor relations, and comparative government.
Biographical Sketch
Henry (Heinrich) Walter Ehrmann, a political scientist and professor of law, was born in Berlin in 1908. He attended the French Lycée in Berlin before studying Law and Political Science at Berlin University, from which he graduated with a law degree (LL.B.) in 1929. In 1932 Ehrmann obtained a doctorate in jurisprudence at the University of Freiburg, Germany, and was appointed as a judge in Berlin.
In 1933 he was arrested by the Gestapo and sent to the Oranienburg concentration camp for his contacts with the German Social Democratic Party. Ehrmann escaped to Czechoslovakia and eventually fled to France where he was a political refugee from 1934 to 1940 and worked as a journalist, a corresponding member of the Institute for Social Research, Columbia University, New York, and an associate of the International Institute of Social History in Amsterdam. During his stay in France, Ehrmann became a member of the Neues Beginnen, a small underground anti-fascist group of German exiles. Having been interned as a German in 1940, he managed to escape with his wife (née Claire Sachs) through Spain and Portugal to the USA. After coming to the United States, Ehrmann became a research associate on the graduate faculty of the "University in Exile", the New School for Social Research in New York City (1940). Between 1941 and 1943 he was also the editor of "In Re: Germany", published monthly in New York City. From 1943 to 1947 Ehrmann served as a consultant to the Office of War Information and the War Department in Washington, DC, and lectured at re-education courses for selected German prisoners-of-war held at Forts Kearney, Getty and Wetherill, R.I., and Fort Eustis, VA. He was also in charge of the German History Department at Fort Getty, R.I.
In 1947 Ehrmann was appointed associate professor of Political Science at the University of Colorado in Boulder, where he taught until 1961. During his work at the University of Colorado, he took part in an academic freedom case connected with the non-renewal of Morris A. Judd's appointment as instructor in philosophy at the university (1952).
In 1950 Ehrmann participated in a seminar on modern France at the Institute for Advanced Studies in Princeton, NJ. Other positions he held in the 1950s include: a member of the editorial board of the American Political Science Review (1952-1956), a member of the Fulbright Awards Selection Committee (1953-1956), and a consultant to the Social Science division of UNESCO, for which he edited and co-authored a publication, "The Teaching of the Social Sciences in the United States" (1954). Ehrmann also served as a rapporteur for a conference of the International Political Science Association and edited its ensuing volume, "Interest Groups on Four Continents" (1958).
In February 1960, Ehrmann took part in the production of "The Diary of Anne Frank" at the Nomad Playhouse in Boulder, CO. In 1961 he was named Professor of the Year at Boulder. In the same year Ehrmann resigned from the University of Colorado faculty and moved to Dartmouth College in Hanover, NH, where he taught as the Joel Parker Professor of Law and Political Science until 1971. In 1969 he became involved with an academic freedom case at Dartmouth after disciplinary charges were brought against a group of students who prevented a controversial speech on race and genetics at the college ("The Shockley incident"). In 1971 Ehrmann resigned from his position in the Government Department at Dartmouth and accepted a similar post at McGill University in Montreal (1971-1973), where he also chaired a commission responsible for implementing a curriculum reform at the Faculty of Arts.
Apart from the above-mentioned schools, Ehrmann taught as a visiting professor at the University of California at Berkeley and San Diego and in various cities in France (the universities of Bordeaux, Grenoble, Nice and the Sorbonne in Paris) and Germany (the Free University of Berlin, the University of Mannheim, and the Academy of Administration in Bochum).
In 1977 Ehrmann was cited by the French government as a Chevalier de l'Ordre des Palmes Académiques. In 1978 he received an honorary doctor of laws degree from the University of Hartford in Connecticut, and in 1982 an honorary doctorate of philosophy from the University of Mannheim. Ehrmann was a member of the American Civil Liberties Union. He held awards from the Rockefeller Foundation and the Social Science Research Council. Ehrmann died in La Jolla, CA, in 1994.
His major publications include: "Der Mehrgliedrige Tarifvertrag" (1932), "German History in a New Light" (1945), "French Labor from Popular Front to Liberation" (1947), "Organized Business in France" (1957), "Interest Groups on Four Continents" (1958), "Politics in France" (1968), and "Comparative Legal Cultures" (1976).
Chronology:
1908 Born in Berlin, Germany
1926 Graduated from the French Lycée in Berlin
1926-1929 Studies Law, Political Science, History, and Economics at the Universities of Berlin and Freiburg.
1929 Receives a Bachelor of Laws degree at Berlin University
1932 Doctorate in Jurisprudence at the University of Freiburg
1936-1939 Corresponding member (in Paris) of Institute for Social Research, Columbia University, New York City
1936-1940 Research Associate (in Paris) of International Institute for Social History, Amsterdam
1940-1943 Research Associate, Graduate Faculty of Social and Political Science, New School for Social Research, New York City
1941-1943 Editor of "In Re: Germany"
1943-1947 Consultant to the Office of War Information and the War Department in Washington
1945 Head of the German History Department at Fort Getty, Rhode Island
1947-1961 Teaches at the University of Colorado in Boulder
1950 Participates in a seminar on modern France at the Institute for Advanced Studies in Princeton, New Jersey
1952 Morris A. Judd's case at the University of Colorado
1952-1956 Editorial board member, American Political Science Review
1953-1956 Member, Fulbright Awards Selection Committee
1954 Consultant to the Social Science Division of UNESCO
1960 Participates in the production of "The Diary of Anne Frank" at the Nomad Playhouse in Boulder, CO
1961 Chosen Professor of the Year at the University at Colorado in Boulder
1961-1971 Teaches at Dartmouth College in Hanover, New Hampshire
1969 William Shockley's case at Dartmouth College
1971-1973 Teaches at McGill University in Montreal
1977 Awarded the rank of Chevalier de l'Ordre des Palmes Académiques
1978 Receives an honorary Doctorate of Law from the University of Hartford, Connecticut
1982 Receives an honorary Doctorate of Philosophy from the University of Mannheim
1994 December 25, Dies in La Jolla, California
Scope and Contents
The Henry Ehrmann Papers, 1932-1998, are focused on two important aspects of Ehrmann's life: his scholarly career as a political scientist and a professor of law at the University of Colorado in Boulder and Dartmouth College in Hannover, NH, as well as his participation in the program of re-education of German prisoners-of-war in the 1940s. The material also documents Ehrmann's association with other universities and institutions in the United States and Europe. The papers do not provide much information on Ehrmann's private life and on his professional career previous to 1940.
The collection is arranged by subject and consists of the following series: 1) biographical materials (1932-1998), 2) correspondence - divided into two subseries: 2.1) general correspondence (1941-1988) and 2.2) correspondence with the former prisoners-of-war or pertaining to their reeducation program (1945-1950; 1978) 3) materials related to the reeducation program for German prisoners-of-war (1945-1947; 1982), 4) miscellaneous works written by Ehrmann (1931-1989), such as articles, reports, and conference papers, and 5) lectures - divided into two subseries: 5.1) single lectures (1947-1986) and 5.2) university courses and syllabi (1953-1988).
A considerable part of the collection (esp. Ehrmann's correspondence and lectures) is written in German and French. Among biographical materials, there is a copy of Ehrmann's certificate of marriage, diplomas and honors, an autobiographical lecture given by Ehrmann shortly after his arrival in the USA, materials documenting his participation in academic freedom cases at the University of Colorado and Dartmouth College, and a CIA file obtained under the Freedom of Information Act.
Letters from over a hundred former prisoners-of-war whom Ehrmann taught during the reeducation program developed by the War Department form a particularly valuable part of his correspondence. They provide insight into life in Germany during the period of transition from dictatorship to democracy after the Second World War and into German soldiers' adaptation to new circumstances. Letters in the general correspondence subseries are, for the most part, related to Ehrmann's contacts with his fellow scholars and with academic or political institutions.
The reeducation program series contains an extensive historical monograph on the program (including reports, memoranda and instructions, copies of confidential correspondence between the Department of State and the War Department, samples of POW magazines "Der Ruf" and "Auslese", and a supplement on the reeducation of Japanese prisoners-of-war), educational materials (e.g. Ehrmann's lectures on the history of Germany "Deutsche Geschichte im neuem Licht"), and questionnaires used in selecting candidates for the program.
The group of Ehrmann's miscellaneous works includes his reports on France ("Frankreich Berichte") commissioned by the Institute of Social Research in New York (1936-1939), reports on German communities in Latin America written for the Bureau of Latin American Research in Washington, D.C. (1943), and transcripts of radio broadcasts.
Single lectures - given by Ehrmann both in the United States and abroad - are divided into the following subject groups: France, Germany, USA, and International Affairs. Lectures in the university courses and syllabi subseries belong to eight courses: International Law, International Organization, International Law and Organization, Comparative Politics: Europe, Introduction to Political Science - Comparative Politics, Verfassungslehre und Verfassungspraxis in den USA und der französischen fünften Republik, Le Système Politique Français, and Politics in France.
Newspaper clippings, which appear in all but the fifth series, include articles on Ehrmann and his professional activities, articles and letters to newspaper editors written by Ehrmann, materials accompanying his lectures, articles related to the reeducation program of German POWs, as well as clippings from German newspapers sent to Ehrmann by his correspondents.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized as follows:
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by Henry W. Ehrmann in 1987-1988. An additional accession was received from Michael Ehrmann in January 2004.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Military and Armed Conflict; Criminal Justice and Prisons; Anti-Nazi movement.; Labor unions -- France.; Socialism -- Germany.; Political science -- Study and teaching.; Comparative government -- Study and teaching.; Political scientists -- United States.; Political scientists -- France.; Political scientists -- Germany.; Germans -- United States.; Germans -- France.; National socialism.; Prisoners’ writings, German.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Prisoners and prisons.; Prisoners of war -- Germany.; France -- Politics and government.; Germany -- Politics and government.; Ehrmann, Henry Walter, 1908-1994.; Frank, Karl Boromäus, 1893-1969.; Biddle, Francis, 1886-1968.; Lattimore, Owen, 1900-1989.; Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962.; Rosenstock-Huessy, Eugen, 1888-1973.; University of Colorado, Boulder. Department of Political Science.; Dartmouth University. Department of Political Science.; University of California, San Diego. Department of Political Science.; Institute for Social and Economic Research and Policy (Columbia University); New School for Social Research (New York, N.Y.: 1919-1997). Graduate Faculty of Political and Social Science.; Sozialdemokratische Partei Deutschlands.; Gruppe Neu Beginnen.; United States. War Department.
- Biographical Materials, 1932-1998; 1; 16 file folders
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains Ehrmann's autobiographical writings, his CIA file, newspaper clippings of articles on Ehrmann or related to organizations where he worked, and miscellaneous memorabilia (citations, diplomas, and other documents connected with honors he received). There are also some personal records, such as Ehrmann's marriage certificate, passports, death certificate, and materials documenting Ehrmann's involvement in two academic freedom cases (University of Colorado, 1952, Dartmouth College, 1969) as well as a report of the Faculty Planning Committee, chaired by Ehrmann, which was responsible for the curriculum reform at the Faculty of Arts, McGill University.
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Memorabilia, 1932-1983 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 1)
  - CIA file and correspondence relating to the file, 1942-1976 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 2)
  - Newspaper articles on Ehrmann's speeches and lectures, 1948-1972; Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 3)
  - Newspaper articles on Ehrmann or related to institutions where he worked, 1950-1985; Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 4)
  - Curriculum vitae, list of publications, Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 5)
  - University of Colorado: Ehrmann's participation in an academic freedom case, 1952 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 6)
  - Dartmouth College: "the Shockley Incident" -- an academic freedom case, 1969 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 7)
  - McGill University: Curriculum Reform at the Faculty of Arts, 1972 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 8)
  - Honorary degree. University of Hartford, 1978 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 9)
  - Honorary degree. Mannheim University, Germany, 1982 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 10)
  - Honorary degree. Institut d'Études, Paris, 1989 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 11)
  - Premiere of Richard Kaplan's film The Exiles, 1989 September 18 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 12)
  - Death certificate, notices, 1994 December 25 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 13)
  - Obituaries, memorials, 1994-1995 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 14)
  - Memorial service, 1995 April 8 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 15)
  - Memorial conference (Paris, 1998 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 16)
- Correspondence, 1941-1988; 2; 244 file folders
  This series contains extensive correspondence - in English, German, and French - Ehrmann maintained with his colleagues, friends, publishers, other scholars, and various institutions after his arrival in the United States. Letters from former German prisoners-of-war taught by Ehrmann during the reeducation program at Forts Kearney, Getty and Wetherill, R.I., and Fort Eustis, VA. form another significant part of the correspondence series.
  Arranged alphabetically within subseries.
  - General Correspondence, 1941-1988; 2.1; 131 file folders, including 95 individual correspondents and 24 institutions
    General correspondence reflects Ehrmann's professional and private relationships with friends, colleagues, fellow scholars, publishers, editors, and various educational and professional organizations in the United States, France, and Germany. The sub-series contains correspondence with such institutions as the US Senate (including John F. Kennedy's letter to the Ehrmann's), Department of State, and many universities in the USA and abroad. There are also letters from Robert Oppenheimer, Eugen Rosenstock-Huessy, Eleanor Roosevelt, and correspondence that originated in reaction to Ehrmann's letter on Martin Luther King (published in The New York Times in 1969).
    - Abraham, Henry J. (Univ. of Virginia, Charlottesville), 1973; 1976 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 1)
    - Artz, Frederick B. (Oberlin College), 1941; 1944 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 2)
    - Ascoli, Max ("The Reporter"), 1944-1954 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 3)
    - Baring, Arnulf (Freie Universität Berlin), 1972-1976 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 4)
    - Barnard, Robert C. (Dept of Justice), 1944 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 5)
    - Barre, Raymond, 1959 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 6)
    - Baruzy, Pierre, 1959 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 7)
    - Bendix, Reinhard, 1985-1986 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 8)
    - Black, Hugo L., 1952 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 9)
    - Bloch-Lainé, François, 1964-1981 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 10)
    - Blumel, André, 1945; 1969 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 11)
    - Bodenheimer, Edgar and Brigitte, 1952; 1979-1987 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 12)
    - Bodiguel, Jean-Luc (Fondation Nationale des Sciences Politiques -- 1981), 1983 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 13)
    - Bradley, Philips, 1942-1947; Undated (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 14)
    - Bundy, McGeorge (Harvard Univ), 1952; 1954 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 15)
    - Cherrington, Ben M., 1951; 1952 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 16)
    - Cole, Taylor, 1948-1952 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 17)
    - Colton, Joel (Duke University), 1952 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 18)
    - Cousins, Norman, 1952 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 19)
    - Cuthbertson, Stuart (Univ. of Colorado, Boulder), 1949-1950; Undated (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 20)
    - Ducamin, Bernard (Conséil d'État), 1981-1986 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 21)
    - Duverger, Maurice, 1952; 1974 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 22)
    - Dyde, W. F. (Univ. of Colorado, Boulder), 1952; Undated (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 23)
    - Ehrmann, Herbert B., 1969 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 24)
    - Faye, P.-L, 1948-1959; Undated (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 25)
    - Fisher, H. H. (The Hoover Institute), 1952; 1954 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 26)
    - Foitzik, Jan, 1985-1986 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 27)
    - Friedrich, Carl J. (Harvard University), 1949; 1952 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 28)
    - Gange, John (Univ. of Virginia, Charlottesville), 1952 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 29)
    - Gaxie, Daniel, 1974-1987; Undated (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 30)
    - Gershoy, Leo, 1968; Undated (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 31)
    - Goguel, François, 1954-1988 [?]; Undated (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 32)
    - Gournay, Bernard, 1968-1983; Undated (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 33)
    - Grosser, Alfred (Fondation Nationale des Sciences Politiques), 1979-1980; Undated (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 34)
    - Guerard, Albert (Stanford University), 1942-1949 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 35)
    - Hazard, John N. (Columbia University), 1949-1952 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 36)
    - Helmich, Ursula, 1977 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 37)
    - Hempel, Henri Jacob, 1986 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 38)
    - Herring, Pendleton (Social Science Research Council, N.Y), 1965; Undated (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 39)
    - Hirsch-Weber, Wolfgang, 1973-1986 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 40)
    - Hoeniger, Heinrich, 1944; 1947 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 41)
    - Hollerbach, Alexander (Universität Freiburg i. Br), 1980-1984 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 42)
    - Hovde, Bryn J. (The New School for Social Research), 1947; 1949 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 43)
    - Humphrey, Hubert H. (United States Senate, 1952 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 44)
    - Johnson, Edwin C. (U.S. Senate), 1949; 1952 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 45)
    - Jones, Howard Mumford, 1945-1949 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 46)
    - Kaiser, Philip M. (Dept of Labor), 1950; 1951 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 47)
    - Kemeny, John G. (Dartmouth College), 1971; 1978 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 48)
    - Kennan, George (Institute for Advanced Study), 1951 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 49)
    - Kennedy, John F., 1959 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 50)
    - King, Jerry [?], 1968-1982 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 51)
    - Kohn, Hans (The City College, N.Y), 1949; 1952 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 52)
    - Laitin, David and Delia, 1980-1987 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 53)
    - Lancelot, Alain, 1983; Undated (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 54)
    - Laroque, Michel, 1981 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 55)
    - Laroque, Pierre (Conséil d'État), 1958-1992; Undated (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 56)
    - Lattimore, Owen (Johns Hopkins Univ., Baltimore), 1952 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 57)
    - Litchfield, Edward H., 1952; 1954 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 58)
    - Loewenstein, Karl (Amherst College), 1944; 1968 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 59)
    - Mayer, Daniel (President of the Conseil Constitutionnel), 1983 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 60)
    - McHendrie, Douglas, 1948-1952; Undated (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 61)
    - Merle, Marcel (Université de Paris I), 1968-1987 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 62)
    - Meuter, Paul, 1992 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 63)
    - Meyer, Richard A., 1941; 1952 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 64)
    - Meyerhof, Walter, 1940 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 65)
    - Meynaud, J., 1950-1954 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 66)
    - Mommse, Ted (Princeton Univ), 1949; 1952 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 67)
    - Mosely, Philip E. (Columbia Univ), 1949-1968 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 68)
    - Odegard, Peter H. (Univ. of California, Berkeley), 1948; 1950 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 69)
    - Oppenheimer, J. Robert, 1950 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 70)
    - Perkins, Frances (U.S. Civil Service Commission), 1947 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 71)
    - Pollock, James K. (Univ. of Michigan, Ann Arbor), 1951; 1964 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 72)